About Our Project

In this project, we seek to explore how nationalism is expressed through the colonial narrative of “folk songs” in the American West and German Southwest Afrika, present-day Namibia. Our team analyzed a corpus of texts to understand the expression of collective colonial identity in both Germany and the US, and how those contexts may be related. We determined that songs would be particularly effective in communicating the collective ideas of these groups because they are composed for the “common man”. Soldiers and settlers alike were supposed to identify with these songs, and the songs themselves were meant to solidify and encourage their concepts of national identity.

One of the main goals in analyzing these songs is understanding what these collective ideas are and how they may translate to the justification of violence. In many of the songs, you might notice derogatory, violent, or negative language surrounding the cultures that were native to the land being colonized. Genocide is part of the history of colonization in both the US and German South-west Africa. Can songs offer us an insight into the mentality and hatred that supported and encouraged these inhuman acts of violence? Can we see expressions of nationalism that promote an “us-vs-them” mentality that laid the seeds of racism, xenophobia and eventually acts of genocide? Go to our historical context tab to learn more about this, and the relationship between the American West and the German Southwest.

Through our research, we determined that colonization’s main tenets include possession of land, resources, bodies, and labor based upon concepts of racial/ethnic superiority that are driven by a love of country, unity and the “us vs. them” mentality. When analyzing our texts, we decided to search for five main themes: homeland, violence, national unity, possession, and other significant acts. Within these main categories, we evaluated if song lyrics were instances of, for example, patriotism or xenophobia. We also made note of whether these statements had positive or negative inflections. Through collecting data based on the metrics we choose to categorize, we hope to identify patterns and to compare types of nationalism that American and German colonizers expressed.

You can read more about this and our analysis under the results and conclusions pages.

About The Texts

American Songs

The songs that make up this Corpus were all selected from Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads, which was first published in 1910. We choose this source because it was easily accessible and was already digitalized on the Project Guttenberg site. We selected songs whose content dealt directly with either expansion and possession of land or with settlers’ relationships with native peoples. You will notice that this corpus is significantly larger than the German songs, this is due to multiple historical and practical reasons. First, we had a much easier time finding and accessing American folk songs online. The American period of expansion was also much longer and has been celebrated in popular culture to this day. This accounts for a greater public interest in these songs, which likely contributed to higher rates of publication and circulation. Due to the time and resource restrictions of this project, we embraced this disparity and went forward with a greater amount of American songs.

German Songs (English)

The primary source we used for the German songs was Deutsche Reiter in Südwest: Selbsterlebnisse aus den Kämpfen in Deutsch-Südwestafrika (German Riders in the Southwest: experiences from the wars in German Southwest Africa) by Friedrich Freiherr von Dincklage-Campe and was published in 1909. This book, which also includes illustrations by C. Becker, V. Huen, and O. Merté, was the inspiration for this project. It details the years of war and genocide from 1904 and 1907, and the songs and illustrations (one of which you will find on our home page) made it apparent that there were many themes and tropes in common with depictions of the American “wild west”. The second song, Das Südwesterlied, was the only song we could find readily available on the internet that talked specifically about soldiers’ experiences in German Southwest Africa and that was not taken from the book.

German Songs (German)

We choose to include the German songs as a language reference because we did our own translations. However, we felt it would be more effective for our project if the markup of the songs was in the same language. We felt this would make our analysis clearer and more accessible.

The Songs of Colonization - American

About the Songs

The songs that make up this Corpus were all selected from Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads,[1] which was first published in 1910. We choose this source because it was easily accessible and was already digitalized on the Project Guttenberg site. We selected songs whose content dealt directly with either expansion and possession of land or with settlers’ relationships with native peoples. You will notice that this corpus is significantly larger than the German songs, this is due to multiple historical and practical reasons. First, we had a much easier time finding and accessing American folk songs online. The American period of expansion was also much longer and has been celebrated in popular culture to this day. This accounts for a greater public interest in these songs, which likely contributed to higher rates of publication and circulation. Due to the time and resource restrictions of this project, we embraced this disparity and went forward with a greater amount of American songs.

Contents

1. THE BUFFALO HUNTERS 2. THE COWMAN'S PRAYER 3. HERE'S TO THE RANGER! 4. TEXAS RANGERS 5. NEW NATIONAL ANTHEM 6. WESTWARD HO 7. SIOUX INDIANS 8. THE OLD SCOUT'S LAMENT

Key

Significant Elements

Violence
Significant phrase
Homeland
National Unity
Possession

Moods

Positive
Negative
Ambiguous

*Hover over elements with a dotted line to see more specific information about attributes.*

THE BUFFALO HUNTERS

Come all you pretty girls, to you these lines I'll write,
We are going to the rangecelebratory in which we take delight;
We are going on the range as we poor hunters do,
And the tender-footed fellows can stay at home with you.

It's all of the day long as we go tramping roundexploring
In search of the buffalo that we may shoot him downresources ;
Our guns upon our shoulders, our belts of forty rounds,
We send them up Salt River to some happy hunting grounds.

Our gameresources , it is the antelope, the buffalo, wolf, and deer,
Who roam the wide prairies without a single fear;
We rob him of his robe and think it is no harmresources ,
To buy us food and clothing to keep our bodies warm.

The buffalo, he is the noblest of the band,
He sometimes rejects in throwing up his hand.
His shaggy main thrown forward, his head raised to the sky,
He seems to say, "We're coming, boys; so hunter, mind your eye."

Our fires are made of mesquite roots, our beds are on the ground;
Our houses made of buffalo hidesresources , we make them tall and round;
Our furniture is the camp kettle, the coffee pot, and pan,
Our chuck it is both bread and meat, mingled well with sand.

Our neighbors are the Cheyennes, the 'Rapahoes, and Siouxcoexisting ,
Their mode of navigation is a buffalo-hide canoe.
And when they come upon you they take you unawareperpetrator: native, victim: settler ,
And such a peculiar way they have of raising hunter's hair.

THE COWMAN'S PRAYER

Now, O Lord, please lend me thine ear,
The prayer of a cattleman to hear,
No doubt the prayers may seem strange,
But I want you to bless our cattle rangeland .

Bless the round-ups year by year,
And don't forget the growing steer;
Water the lands with brooks and rills
For my cattle that roam on a thousand hills.

Prairie fires, won't you please stop?
Let thunder roll and water drop.
It frightens me to see the smoke;
Unless it's stopped, I'll go dead broke.

As you, O Lord, my herdresources behold,
It represents a sack of gold;
I think at least five cents a pound
Will be the price of beef the year around.

One thing more and then I'm through,--
Instead of one calf, give my cows two.
I may pray different from other men
But I've had my say, and now, Amen.

HERE'S TO THE RANGER!

He leaves unplowed his furrow,
He leaves his books unread
For a life of tented freedom
By lure of danger led.
He's first in the hour of peril,
He's gayest in the dance,
Like the guardsman of old Englandpatriotism
Or the beau sabreur of Francepatriotism .

He stands our faithful bulwarkloyality
Against our savage foehating, xenophobia ;
Through lonely woodland places
Our children come and go;
Our flocks and herdsresources untended
O'er hill and valley roam,
The Ranger in the saddle
Means peacebelonging for us at homepeace .

Behold our smiling farmsteadsland
Where waves the golden grain!
Beneath yon tree, earth's bosomloving
Was dark with crimson stain.
That bluff the death-shot echoed
Of husband, father, slainperpetrator: ambiguous, victim: settler!
God grant such sight of horror
We never see again!

The gay and hardy Ranger,
His blanket on the ground,
Lies by the blazing camp-fire
While song and tale goes round;
And if one voice is silent,
One fails to hear the jest,
They know his thoughts are absent
With her who loves him best.

Our statepossessive , her sons confess it,
That queenly, star-crowned brow,
Has darkened with the shadow
Of lawlessness ere now;
And men of evil passions
On her reproach have laid,
But that the ready Ranger
Rode promptly to her aid.

He may not win the laurel
Nor trumpet tongue of fame;
But beauty smiles upon him,
And ranchmen bless his namereverant .
Then here's to the Texas Rangerreverant ,
Past, present and to come!
Our safety from the savagexenophobia ,
The guardian of our homepatriotism .

TEXAS RANGERS

Come, all you Texas rangers, wherever you may be,
I'll tell you of some troubles that happened unto me.
My name is nothing extra, so it I will not tell,--
And here's to all you rangersreverant , I am sure I wish you well.

It was at the age of sixteen that I joined the jolly band,
We marched from San Antonio down to the Rio Grande.
Our captain he informed us, perhaps he thought it right,
"Before we reach the station, boys, you'll surely have to fight."

And when the bugle sounded our captain gave commandloyality ,
"To arms, to arms," he shouted, "and by your horses stand."
I saw the smoke ascending, it seemed to reach the sky;
The first thought that struck me, my time had come to die.

I saw the Indians comingother , I heard them give the yell;
My feelings at that moment, no tongue can ever tell.
I saw the glittering lances, their arrows round me flewperpetrator: native, victim: settler ,
And all my strength it left me and all my courage too.

We foughtperpetrator: ambiguous, victim: ambiguous full nine hours before the strife was o'er,
The like of dead and wounded I never saw before.
And when the sun was rising and the Indians they had fled,
We loaded up our rifles and counted up our dead.

And all of us were wounded, our noble captainreverant slain,
And the sun was shining sadly across the bloody plain.
Sixteen as brave rangersreverant as ever roamed the West
Were buried by their comradessolidarity with arrows in their breastperpetrator: native, victim: settler .

'Twas then I thought of motherlonging, who to me in tears did say,
"To you they are all strangers, with me you had better stay."
I thought that she was childish, the best she did not know;
My mind was fixed on ranging and I was bound to gobelonging .

Perhaps you have a mother, likewise a sister too,
And maybe you have a sweetheart to weep and mourn for you;
If that be your situation, although you'd like to roam,
I'd advise you by experience, you had better stay at homecomplaint .

I have seen the fruits of rambling, I know its hardships well;
I have crossed the Rocky Mountains, rode down the streets of hell;
I have been in the great Southwest where the wild Apachesxenophobia roam,
And I tell you from experience you had better stay at homecomplaint .

And now my song is ended; I guess I have sung enough;
The life of a ranger I am sure is very tough.
And here's to all you ladies, I am sure I wish you well,
I am bound to go a-rangingbelonging , so ladies, fare you well.

NEW NATIONAL ANTHEM

My countrycomplaint , 'tis of thee,
Land where things used to becomplaint
So cheap, we croak.
Land of the mavericksland ,
Land of the puncher's tricksland ,
Thy culture-inroad pricks
The hide of this peeler-bloke.

Some of the punchers swear
That what they eat and wear
Takes all their calves.
Others vow that they
Eat only once a day
Jerked beef and prairie hay
Washed down with tallow salves.

These salty-dogs but crave
To pull them out the grave
Just one Kiowa spurxenophobia .
They know they still will dine
On flesh and beef the time;
But give us, Lord divine,
One "hen-fruit stir."

Our father's landpossessive , with thee,
Best trails of libertyreverant ,
We chose to stop.
We don't exactly like
So soon to henceward hike,
But hell, we'll take the pike
If this don't stop.

WESTWARD HO

I love not Colorado
Where the faro table grows,
And down the desperado
The rippling Bourbon flows;

Nor seek I fair Montana
Of bowie-lunging fame;
The pistol ring of fair Wyoming
I leave to nobler game.

Sweet poker-haunted Kansas
In vain allures the eye;
The Nevada rough has charms enough
Yet its blandishments I fly.

Shall Arizona woo me
Where the meek Apache bides?xenophobia
Or New Mexico where natives growxenophobia
With arrow-proof insides?

Nay,'tis where the grizzlies wander
And the lonely diggers roam,
And the grim Chinese from the squatter fleesxenophobia
That I'll make my humble home.possessive

I'll chase the wild tarantula
And the fierce cayote I'll dare,
And the locust grim, I'll battle him
In his native wildwood lair.

Or I'll seek the gulch desertedexploring
And dream of the wild Red man,xenophobia
And I'll build a cot on a corner lot
And get rich as soon as I can.

SIOUX INDIANS

I'll sing you a song, though it may be a sad one,
Of trials and troubles and where they first begun;
I left my dear kindred, my friends, and my home,longing
Across the wild deserts and mountains to roam.exploring

I crossed the Missouri and joined a large trainexploring
Which bore us over mountain and valley and plain;exploring
And often of evenings out hunting we'd go
To shoot the fleet antelope and wild buffalo.resources

We heard of Sioux Indiansxenophobia all out on the plains
A-killing poor drivers and burning their trains,perpetrator: native, victim: settler --
A-killing poor drivers with arrows and bow,perpetrator: native, victim: settler
When captured by Indians no mercy they show.perpetrator: native, victim: settler

We traveled three weeks till we came to the Platteexploring
And pitched out our tents at the end of the flat,land
We spread down our blankets on the green grassy ground,land
While our horses and mules were grazing around.

While taking refreshment we heard a low yell,
The whoop of Sioux Indiansxenophobia coming up from the dell;
We sprang to our rifles with a flash in each eye,perpetrator: settler, victim: native
"Boys," says our brave leader, "we'll fight till we die."solidarity

They made a bold dash and came near to our train
And the arrows fell around us like hail and like rain,perpetrator: native, victim: settler
But with our long rifles we fed them cold lead perpetrator: settler, victim: native
Till many a brave warrior around us lay dead. perpetrator: settler, victim: native

We shot their bold chief at the head of his band.perpetrator: settler, victim: native
He died like a warrior with a gun in his hand.perpetrator: settler, victim: native
When they saw their bold chief lying dead in his gore,perpetrator: settler, victim: native
They whooped and they yelled and we saw them no more.

With our small band,--there were just twenty-four,--
And the Sioux Indians there were five hundred or more,--
We fought them with courage; we spoke not a word,perpetrator: settler, victim: native
Till the end of the battle was all that was heard.

We hitched up our horses and we started our train;
Three more bloody battles this trip on the plain;perpetrator: settler, victim: native
And in our last battle three of our brave boysbrotherhood fell,perpetrator: native, victim: settler
And we left them to rest in a green, shady dell.

THE OLD SCOUT'S LAMENT

Come all of you, my brother scouts,brotherhood
And join me in my song;
Come, let us sing together
Come all of you, my brother scouts,brotherhood
And join me in my song;
Come, let us sing together
Though the shadows fall so long.

Of all the old frontiersmenreverant
That used to scour the plain,
There are but very few of them
That with us yet remain.solidarity

Day after day they're dropping off,
They're going one by one;
Our clan is fast decreasing,solidarity
Our race is almost run.solidarity

There were many of our number
That never wore the blue,
But, faithfully, they did their part,loyality
As brave men, tried and true.brotherhood
But, faithfully, they did their part,loyality
As brave men, tried and true.brotherhood

They never joined the army,
But had other work to do
In piloting the coming folks,
To help them safely through.

But, brothers, we are falling,brotherhood
Our race is almost run;solidarity
The days of elk and buffalo
And beaver traps are gone.

Oh the days of elk and buffalo
It fills my heart with painnostalgic
To know these days are past and gonenostalgicnostalgic
To never come again.

We foughtperpetrator: settler, victim: native the red-skin rascalsxenophobia
Over valley, hill, and plain;
We fought him in the mountain top,perpetrator: settler, victim: native
And fought him down again.perpetrator: settler, victim: native
It fills my heart with pain
To know these days are past and gone
To never come again.

We fought the red-skin rascalsperpetrator: native, victim: settler
Over valley, hill, and plain;
We fought him in the mountain top,perpetrator: native, victim: settler
And fought him down againperpetrator: native, victim: settler .

These fighting days are over;
The Indian yell resoundsperpetrator: settler, victim: native
No more along the border;
Peace sends far sweeter soundspeace.

But we found great joy, old comradesbrotherhood
To hear, and make it die;
We won bright homes for gentle ones,land
And now, our West,land good-bye. nostalgic
But we found great joy, old comradescelebratory
To hear, and make it die;
We won bright homes for gentle ones,land ,
And now, our West,land good-bye.nostalgic

Sources

Lomax, John A. 1. Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads, Collected by John A. Lomax . with an Introduction by Barrett Wendell. The Macmillan company, 1927, New York (State), 1927.

Conclusions

National Unity

We examined national unity in the songs within the contexts of brotherhood, loyalty, pride, patriotism, and solidarity. We found that there was a greater expression of national unity in the German songs and that these expressions were more centered around loyalty whereas the American songs had a stronger focus on brotherhood and solidarity. We believe that this is once again indicative of the political and social contexts of an overseas versus a continuous empire. We also think this is indicative of the fact that Germans had a stronger connection to Germany and the fatherland whereas the Americans were simply connected through their interactions with other settlers. The Germans were serving in an army that required loyalty and reverence to the empire. The same thing was not required of Americans, as many of them choose to band together in and form communities.

Violence

We examined depictions of violence between groups of people within the songs as a way to understand how the settlers and soldiers viewed acts of violence, in hopes that it would give us insight into their perspective and how it connects to their ideas about nationalism and their claim to the land they occupied. Many instances of violence were committed upon animals, but this was also interesting to us as it reveals how they perceived the land’s resources. The German songs overall had less violence than the American songs, and that violence more often was ambiguous on which group either the perpetrator or victim belonged to. We believe this might be because they were engaging in formalized, controlled military violence. We know that they raided villages, fought in wars, and committed genocide but because the violence took place in a military context, their relationship to it was likely very different than for settlers who embraced and took pride in the idea of lawless violence.

Xenophobia

We coded for instances of xenophobia when native people were directly mentioned in the songs in derogatory ways or hateful contexts. Although there were many mentions of native people in the American songs, the overall percentages showed that there were more instances of xenophobia in the German songs. We think that this could be due to geographical contexts. The American settlers were no doubt highly xenophobic and racist and often acted on these feelings, but why would it be less of a focus in their songs? Perhaps the Germans were more focused on this element because they were part of a continuous empire. Germany was separated by thousands of miles of land and oceans. This was also a time when more formalized theories on race and racial hierarchies became more prevalent. The Germans even inflicted medical experimentation on the native peoples and sent their body parts to Europe for eugenics research. Both groups made xenophobia, the fear and hatred of the other, a defining aspect of their identity. However, perhaps the Germans were more focused on this difference, and perhaps it served them more to spread the ideas of xenophobia in the specific times and contexts of the songs we selected.

We coded for mentions of homeland after noticing several references to both the new home and the country or place of origin of the settlers. When examining homeland, we wanted to see if references to homeland had positive, negative or ambiguous connotations to get a better sense of what settlers’ connection to the land was like. We found that the mentions of homeland in the American Songs tended to be more negative, but both groups had around the same percentage of positive mentions. Overall, you may notice that many songs talk about the harsh conditions of the land, but when they directly reference the homeland, the depictions are overwhelmingly positive. We see many examples where they say that they love the home despite how harsh it is and have a sense of pride surrounding it. The fact that positive depictions of the homeland are in the majority tells us that settlers and colonial soldiers had an emotional connection to the land and saw it as their own.

info here

When coding for possession, we between land, people, resources, and labor. Our results show that in both German and American contexts, land and resource possession was by far the most mentioned. We know that historically all four categories were common, especially in German Southwest Africa but we can only speculate as to why possession of people and labor were not mentioned in songs. Perhaps they did not fit into the heroic narrative, or maybe there are more songs not in our corpus with different themes that do mention these circumstances.

info here

The Songs of Colonization - German

Contents

1. Afrikanisches Reiterlied 2. Das Sudwesterlied 3. Schutztruppenlied

Afrikanisches Reiterlied

Hallo, ich treck mit Reiterlust
Die Pad entlang zu Pferd!
Das Herz frohlockt in weiter Brust,
Gleichwie an Mutters Herd!
Es kennt nicht Sorg‘, es kennt nicht Plag‘,
Kein Reiter grämet sich.
Und dennoch ich voll Sehnsucht frag‘:
Wann kehr‘ zur Heimat ich?

Und reit‘ ich so de Pad entlang
Im bunten Sonnenschein,
Durch blauen Ather tönt mein Sang
Dann in den Busch hinein
Er trägt das Lied in alle Welt,
was grad mein Herz erfüllt.
Doch merkt, dass mir kein Lied gefällt,
was meinen Lieb nicht gilt.

Das Kudu und das Wildebeest,
Der Gemsbock und der Strauß,
Ich scheuch‘ sie auf aus ihrem Nest
Und schieß sie mir zum Schmaus.
Bei Hottentotten, Hereros,
Find‘ tausend Frauen ich,
Und dennoch sehn‘ ich immer bloß
Zu meinen Liebchen mich.

Durch Berg und Tal hinauf, hinab,
So reit‘ ich fort und fort,
hinauf, hinab im Schritt und Trab,
So geht’s von Ort zu Ort.
Auch den Galopp verschmäh‘ ich nicht.
Frei liegt die Pad vor mir!
Doch ist die Heimat erst in Sicht,
Zum Halten ich Parier‘!

Das Sudwesterlied

Hart wie Kameldornholz ist unser Land
Und trocken sind seine Riviere.
Die Klippen, sie sind von der Sonne verbrannt
Und scheu sind im Busch die Tiere.
|: Und sollte man uns fragen:
Was hält euch denn hier fest?
Wir könnten nur sagen:
Wir lieben Südwest! :|

Doch unsre Liebe ist teuer bezahlt
Trotz allem, wir lassen dich nicht
Weil unsere Sorgen überstrahlt
Der Sonne hell leuchtendes Licht.
|: Und sollte man uns fragen:
Was en euch en hier fest?
Wir könnten nur sagen:
Wir lieben Südwest!

Und kommst du selber in unser Land
Und hast seine Weiten gesehen
Und hat unsre Sonne ins Herz dir gebrannt
Dann kannst du nicht wieder gehen.
|: Und sollte man uns fragen:
Was hält euch denn hier fest?
Wir könnten nur sagen:
Wir lieben Südwest! :|

Schutztruppenlied

„Ich bin ein junges Reiterblut – in kaiserlichem Sold, –
Trag‘ auf dem Ohre keck den Hut, – frag‘ nicht nach Lieb‘ und Gold. –
Hab‘ unter mir ein flottes Pferd – und führ‘ ein gut Gewehr, –
Was sonst der Himmel mir beschert, – das wiegt bei mir nicht schwer. –
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – zum Schutze sind wir da. –

Brennt noch so stark der Sonne Glut – auf heißem Wüstensand, –
Wir krempen um den breiten Hut – und ziehn vergnügt durchs Land; –
Quält uns der Durst auch noch so sehr, – quält uns der Hunger schier, –
Wir nehmen’s alle nicht so schwer; – den alle denken wir: --
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – zum Schutze sind wir da. –

Und haben wir so manche Nacht, – zu Fuß und auch zu Pferd –
Dem Schlaf getrotzt und treu gewacht, – es hat uns nicht beschwert. –
Für deutsche Bruder tun wir’s gern, – und Stolz füllt unsre Brust, –
Für unsern Kaiser, unsern Herrn; – den wir sind uns bewusst: –
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – zum Schutze sind wir da. –

Wir sochten schon so manchen Strauß – im Busch und Felsgeröll –
Mit diesen schwartzen Teufeln aus und färbten rot ihr Fell. –
Sie rissen aus, wir hinterdrein – soweit der Himmel blau, –
Und holten wir sie selten ein, sie wissen doch genau: –
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – zum Schutze sind wir da. –

Doch ach, so mancher Kamerad – in voller Lebenskraft, –
Bei todeskühner Reitertat – ward er dahingerafft. –
Für unsern Kaiser, für das Reich – gab er dahin sein Blut, –
Auf sein Gesicht, so todesbleich, da legten wir den Hut. –
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – zum Schutze sind wir da. –

Und kommt auch mal an uns die Reih‘, – wir bleiben unverzagt; –
In jedem Kampfe wird aufs neu – das Leben frisch gewagt, –
Wir kämpfen ja für deutsche Macht, für deutsche Herrlichkeit! –
Der fernen Heimat wird gedacht – treulich in Freud‘ und Lied. –
Wir dienen dir, lieb Vaterland, – im Südwestafrika; –
Schutztruppe werden wir genannt, – Schutztruppe hoch, hurra!. –

Historical Context

American Colonial History

North America was first colonized in 1607, with the founding of Jamestown. What followed was centuries of conflict between indigenous peoples and European colonizers which led to massive population losses and the genocide of many Native American tribes. Though colonization was around for a long time, the move of American settlers westward that has been glamorized in movies, plays, and music started after the revolutionary war when the U.S. was founded in 1776. The legacy of Westward expansion fueled by the belief in manifest destiny lasted from 1803, when the Louisiana Purchase was signed, until the early 1900s.[1]

Many of the settlers who moved out west in search of economic opportunity and land, believed in American Exceptionalism. This was the belief that the west was filled with empty, unused land, and that saw the native peoples as “savages” who didn’t know how to properly use it.[2] The reality was of course much different, and the idea that they had a rightful claim to the land had detrimental effects on the native peoples. Despite this brutality, the idea of the American west and life on the frontier became idealized. In his article titled “Capturing the American West: The Cowboy Song and the Archive,” Michael Slowik writes: “during the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, essays, frontier plays, and novels all helped shape the belief that the cowboy was a key representation of "true" American character.”[3]

German Fantasy

The popularity of the image of the Cowboy was not contained only to the United States. In fact, this image became wildly popular in the entertainment industry in Germany. Karl May was a popular author whose books and plays depicting the American frontier, which he had never visited, sparked a cultural phenomenon in Germany still seen today.[4] Among others, May’s depictions of the American west created collective German fantasies about colonization and imperial expansion.[5]

There is evidence, not only that German fascination with the American West was a factor in popular support for overseas expansion, but also that it influenced the way that Colonial Soldiers treated the Herero and Nama ethnic groups during a war from 1904-1907, which escalated into what is now considered the first genocide of the 20th century.[6] The German colonial government looked to and actively researched American policies concerning the extermination of Native Americans in order to use these policies in their own campaign of genocide. This included the relocation of Herero, Nama, and other ethnic groups onto reservations. These groups were forced to give up their traditional cultural practices and convert to Christianity.[7] Cultural artifacts and even human remains were stolen and shipped to European and American research institutions and museums. Survivors of the genocide were rounded up and sent to forced labor camps where they were subject to medical experimentation.[8] These unthinkable policies were tolerated by the German people because the same practices in the American West were so idealized.[9]

German Colonial History

But why was this colonial fantasy so potent in Germany? It is important to consider that Germany was a new nation, formed only in 1871, a century after the United States. Colonization was an attractive process that could at once help form a sense of national pride and ensure that Germany could compete with other European imperial nations. Germany claimed the territory of German Southwest Africa, along with other land parcels in the Berlin conference of 1884, seen as the beginning of the “scramble for Africa”, where remaining territory on the African continent was partitioned among European Imperial powers.[10] The expansion and appropriation of land were seen as a way to strengthen the German nation and identity.

Another method used to encourage German national identity was evoking the romantic depictions of courtly culture and heroic deeds of medieval Germany. For example, Richard Wagner’s famous four-part opera Der Ring des Nibelungen was based on ancient German mythology and written in 1876.[11] Ballads resurfaced as popular forms of writing around this time as well.[12] These stories, which were sung in verse form set to music had been popular in medieval Germany and often drew upon themes of heroic knights and courtly love that would inspire a sense of German national pride again in the 19th century. The Folk songs and German Reiterlieder we are analyzing through this project are reminiscent of very similar themes and structures. They are songs that have a story-like structured narrative that romanticizes the landscape and the bravery of soldiers and settlers. They are written with the purpose of reinforcing new myths that glorified nationalistic ideas of exploration and exploitation under colonialism.

Continuous vs. Overseas Empires

These two very different histories, although one was clearly influenced by the other, point to very important differences in forms of nationalism and colonial rule. It is important to consider even the geography of the areas. The Americans were expanding westward in order to establish a continuous empire. Ideas of exceptionalism and the American dream underline that the people in this movement had a strong sense of belonging and subscribed thoroughly to the American National narrative. In fact, they embodied it. The German empire, however, was overseas. Germany and German Southwest Africa were separated by land and water, and this changed how people perceived the land. German colonization of the area was also pushed forward by soldiers, who were fighting in the name of the German government, rather than settlers fighting for their own claims to land.

Sources

Editors, History com. “Westward Expansion.” HISTORY. Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.history.com/topics/westward-expansion/westward-expansion.
Guettel, Jens-Uwe. “FROM THE FRONTIER TO GERMAN SOUTH-WEST AFRICA: GERMAN COLONIALISM, INDIANS, AND AMERICAN WESTWARD EXPANSION*.” Modern Intellectual History 7, no. 3 (November 2010): 523–52. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1479244310000223.
Slowik, Michael. “Capturing the American Past: The Cowboy Song and the Archive.” The Journal of American Culture 35, no. 3 (2012): 207–18. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1542-734X.2012.00808.x.
Galchen, Rivka. “Wild West Germany | The New Yorker.” Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2012/04/09/wild-west-germany.
Zantop, Susanne. Colonial Fantasies: Conquest, Family, and Nation in Precolonial Germany, 1770-1870. Post-Contemporary Interventions. Durham, N.C: Duke University Press, 1997.
UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK v. FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY, Civ. No. 17-0062 (NY, 2018)
Breure, J., 1999, 'Ancestors: A challenge to the Oruuano Church of Namibia', MTh dissertation, Dept. of Missiology, University of South Africa
UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK v. FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY, Civ. No. 17-0062 (NY, 2018)
Guettel, Jens-Uwe. “FROM THE FRONTIER TO GERMAN SOUTH-WEST AFRICA: GERMAN COLONIALISM, INDIANS, AND AMERICAN WESTWARD EXPANSION*.” Modern Intellectual History 7, no. 3 (November 2010): 523–52. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1479244310000223.
Wallace, M., & Kinahan, J. (2011). A history of Namibia: From the beginning to 1990. New York: Columbia University Press.
Encyclopedia Britannica. “Der Ring Des Nibelungen | Summary, Characters, & Facts.” Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.britannica.com/topic/Der-Ring-des-Nibelungen.
Lord, Albert Bates. The Singer of Tales. Third edition. Publications of the Milman Parry Collection of Oral Literature 4. Cambridge, MA : Washington, DC: Milman Parry Collection of Oral Literature ; Center for Hellenic Studies, 2019.

Sources

References

BoseFritz, and Bruno Nettl. “German Folk Ballads.” Midwest Folklore 7, no. 4 (1957): 207–13.
Breure, J., 1999, 'Ancestors: A challenge to the Oruuano Church of Namibia', MTh dissertation, Dept. of Missiology, University of South Africa
Dincklage-Campe, Friedrich Freiherr von. Deutsche Reiter in Südwest: Selbsterlebnisse aus den Kämpfen in Deutsch-Südwestafrika: nach Persönlichen Berichten. Berlin; Leipzig; Wien; Stuttgart: Bong, 1908. http://tinyurl.gale.com/tinyurl/BzJKu0.
Editors, History com. “Westward Expansion.” HISTORY. Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.history.com/topics/westward-expansion/westward-expansion.
Encyclopedia Britannica. “Der Ring Des Nibelungen | Summary, Characters, & Facts.” Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.britannica.com/topic/Der-Ring-des-Nibelungen.
Galchen, Rivka. “Wild West Germany | The New Yorker.” Accessed April 24, 2020. https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2012/04/09/wild-west-germany.
Guettel, Jens-Uwe. “FROM THE FRONTIER TO GERMAN SOUTH-WEST AFRICA: GERMAN COLONIALISM, INDIANS, AND AMERICAN WESTWARD EXPANSION*.” Modern Intellectual History 7, no. 3 (November 2010): 523–52. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1479244310000223.
Lomax, John A. 1. Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads, Collected by John A. Lomax . with an Introduction by Barrett Wendell. The Macmillan company, 1927, New York (State), 1927.
Lord, Albert Bates. The Singer of Tales. Third edition. Publications of the Milman Parry Collection of Oral Literature 4. Cambridge, MA : Washington, DC: Milman Parry Collection of Oral Literature ; Center for Hellenic Studies, 2019.
Slowik, Michael. “Capturing the American Past: The Cowboy Song and the Archive.” The Journal of American Culture 35, no. 3 (2012): 207–18. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1542-734X.2012.00808.x.
UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK v. FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY, Civ. No. 17-0062 (NY, 2018)
Wallace, M., & Kinahan, J. (2011). A history of Namibia: From the beginning to 1990. New York: Columbia University Press.
Zantop, Susanne. Colonial Fantasies: Conquest, Family, and Nation in Precolonial Germany, 1770-1870. Post-Contemporary Interventions. Durham, N.C: Duke University Press, 1997.

XML

All Songs (mark-up)

Relax NG

Schema

XSLT

Texts
Homeland Graph
National Unity Graph
Possession Graph
Violance Graph
Xenophobia Graph

CSS

Home Page
Navigation Menu and Page Template
Texts
All Other Pages